A Finding Aid to the Peter Blume Papers, 1870-2001, in the Archives of American Art aaa.blumpete
Archives of American Art
Peter Blume papers
1870-2001
aaa.blumpete
Archives of American Art
7.6 Linear feet
The papers of New York and Connecticut painter Peter Blume date from 1870 to 2001 and measure 7.6 linear feet. Found are biographical materials; correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, galleries and institutions, and writers; writings on art by Blume and others; subject files regarding organizations, works of art, exhibitions, and reference files; personal business records; printed material; two scrapbooks; photographs of Blume, family, friends, and works of art; extensive artwork; and material relating to Blume's wife's family, the Cratons.
Blume, Peter, 1906-1992
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 10 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1950-1992 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1926-1992 (1.8 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1929-1986 (0.5 linear feet; Box 3, 9)
Series 4: Subject Files, circa 1930-1988 (0.5 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Series 5: Personal Business and Financial Records, 1934-1983 (0.6 linear feet; Box 4, 9)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1930-1990 (0.7 linear feet; Box 4-5, 9, OV 15-16)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1934-1944 (3 folders; Box 5)
Series 8: Photographs, 1917-circa 1980 (1.1 linear feet; Box 5-6, 9)
Series 9: Artwork, 1932-1984 (2.0 linear feet; Box 6-9, OV 10-14)
Series 10: Craton Family Papers, 1870-2001 (0.2 linear feet; Box 6)
Biographical/Historical note
Russian-born painter and sculptor Peter Blume (1906-1992) was active in New York and Connecticut. His style combined American and European traditions with folk art and surrealism.
Peter Blume was born Piotr Sorek-Sabel in 1906 in Smorgon, Russia. With his family, he emigrated to the United States in 1911 and settled in New York City. Blume studied at the Educational Alliance and the Art Students League in New York. Influenced by folk art, Precisionism, Cubism, and Surrealism, Blume combined European and American painting tradition to create his own style. He was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1932 and travelled to Italy.
In 1934, Blume's South of Scranton (1931) won the first prize at the Carnegie International Exhibition. Later, he exhibited The Eternal City (1937) at the Julian Levy Galleries in Manhattan. With the Section of Painting and Sculpture of the Treasury Department, Blume completed two post office murals in New York and Pennsylvania. Blume was a member of the National Academy of Design and was active with the American Academy in Rome.
Peter Blume married Grace "Ebie" Douglas Craton in 1931. The couple built their home in Sherman, Connecticut. The Blumes travelled the world and kept close relationships with family and friends, such as Ann and Heber Blankenhorn, Malcolm Cowley, and Ned and Nancy Holsten.
Peter Blume died in Connecticut in 1992.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York and Connecticut painter Peter Blume date from 1870 to 2001 and measure 7.6 linear feet. Found are biographical materials; correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, galleries and institutions, and writers; writings on art by Blume and others; subject files regarding organizations, works of art, exhibitions, and reference files; personal business records; printed material; two scrapbooks; photographs of Blume, family, friends, and works of art; extensive artwork; and material relating to Blume's wife's family, the Cratons.
Biographical materials include an award, obituaries, a travel itinerary, and sound recordings and transcripts of interviews of Peter Blume by Alfred H. Barr, Boston College, Harry Boursa, and Visionary Company Magazine.
Correspondence is professional and personal. Letters are from friends, family, artists, writers, galleries, and institutions. Notable correspondents include Kirk Askew, Malcolm Cowley, Peter DeVries, Joseph Hirsch, and Frank A. Trapp, among others. Also found is Grace Blume's correspondence which includes letters to and from Peter Blume and letters from Grace to her family members and friends. The bulk of Grace Blume's correspondence concerns her travels with Blume.
Writings and notes by Blume include a travel journal, lists of works of art, lectures, talks and other writings on art, artists, and friends. Writings by others include theses and scholarly papers about Blume, and include writings by Heber Blankenhorn, Kenneth Burke, Malcolm Cowley, Robert Ulrich Godsoe, Frank Getlein, Michael A. Kelly, and Frank A. Trapp. Also found is criticism on The Rock by school children.
Blume's subject files cover the American Academy of Arts and Letters, American Artists Congress, Heber Blankenhorn, works of art by Blume, exhibitions, and the Connecticut Council on the Arts. Also found are reference files consisting of photographs of artwork by others and clippings.
Personal business and financial records consist of business correspondence with galleries and museums; sales and consignment records; scattered price lists; and receipts and invoices relating to the building and running of Blume's house in Connecticut.
Printed materials include clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for solo and group shows, magazines featuring articles about Blume, posters, and reproductions of works of art.
Scrapbooks include a fragment of a scrapbook from 1942-1944 and a clippings scrapbook from 1934-1939.
Photographs include portraits and snapshots of Peter Blume, Grace Blume, family, friends, travel, parties, pets, homes, landscapes, exhibitions, and works of art. There are also photos of the Askews, the Blankenhorns, the Cowleys, Alfred Eisenstaedt, the Holstens, the Josephsons, Arthur Miller, Georgia O'Keeffe, the Sobys, and Raphael Soyer.
Artwork by Peter Blume includes completed drawings, sketches, doodles, prints, and preliminary drawings for many of his works. Of note are extensive sketches of heads, and preliminary drawings for Recollection of the Flood.
Craton family papers consist of geneological material relating to Grace Blume's brother, James Craton and his wife Catherine Sears Craton. Found are vital records; military records for James and Marshall Craton; correspondence; scattered financial records; clippings; and family photographs.
Related Archival Materials note
Also in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Peter Blume conducted on August 16th, 1983 to May 23rd, 1984 by Robert F. Brown.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Peter Blume papers were donated by in 1993 by Grace Blume, Peter Blume's widow. Additional papers were donated by Catherine Weiss, Jamie Vance, and Leigh Butler in 2010.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection was digitized in 2014 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
American Academy of Arts and Letters.; American Artists' Congress.; Askew, R. Kirk, (Ralph Kirk), 1903-1974; Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1902-1981; Blankenhorn, Heber, 1884-1956; Blume, Grace; Boston College.; Boursa, Harry; Burke, Kenneth, 1897-; Connecticut Council of the Arts.; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-; De Vries, Peter, 1910-1993; Eisenstaedt, Alfred; Getlein, Frank; Godsoe, Robert; Hirsch, Joseph, 1910-1981; Kelly, Michael A.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Trapp, Frank; Visiorary Company Magazine.; Drawings; Interviews; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Prints; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Transcriptions; Travel journals
- Biographical Material, circa 1950-1992; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Scattered biographical records include an award, Peter Blume's obituaries, a map of his birthplace Smorgon, a travel itinerary; and sound recordings and transcripts of interviews with Peter Blume by Alfred H. Barr, Boston College, Harry Bouras, and Visionary Company Magazine. Also found are genealogical records for Grace Blume's family, the Cratons. Researchers should note that the bulk of the Craton family papers are arranged in Series 10.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been partially scanned. Sound recordings have not been scanned.
  - Award, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview with Peter Blume, by Alfred H. Barr, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conversation with Peter Blume for Boston College, circa 1972; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview with Peter Blume by Harry Bouras, WFMT, 1976 January 11; 1976 January 18; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview with Peter Blume by Visionary Company Magazine, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Also includes a map of Blume's birthplace
  - Travel Itinerary, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grace Blume Biographical Material, circa 1950-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Craton Family genealogy
- Correspondence, 1926-1992; Series 2; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-3
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  Professional and personal correspondence is with friends, family, artists, writers, galleries, museums, and institutions. Correspondents include Kirk Askew, Kenneth Burke, Malcolm Cowley, Charles Daniel, Peter and Katinka DeVries, John Hersey, Joseph Hirsch, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, and Frank A. Trapp, among many others. Some works of art have their own folder within correspondence as they reflect Blume's original order. All the letters are in reference to the specified artwork.
  Also found are letters written by Peter Blume to Grace Blume while Blume travelled or was working away from home. There are extensive letters written by Grace Blume to her sister and brother-in-law, Ann and Heber Blankenhorn and to friends, Nancy and Ned Holsten, mostly written during the Blume's travels abroad. Additional correspondence, particularly with galleries and museums, is found among the personal business and financial records. Also, scattered correspondence regarding genealogy is found in Series 10.
  - Albright Art Gallery, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1956-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1947-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Associated Artists of Pittsburgh, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1938-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Art Students League, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Artists Welfare fund, Inc., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Askew, Kirk and Constance, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - A, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Balicki, Mrs. Manan, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Beal, Gifford, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bearden, Romare, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Becker, John, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bernard Davenberg Galleries, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Birmelin, Bob, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Blankenhorn, Heber and Ann, 1937-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    Includes some poetry by Heber Blankenhorn
  - Boyle, Kay, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Breitenbach, Thomas, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brooks, Gladys Von Wyck, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Brooks Memorial Art Gallery, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1943-1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Caffin, Caroline, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Calder, Alexander and Louise, cirac 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Campbell, William, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1934-1950 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cartwell, Bob, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Century Association, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cheever, John, Mary, and Benjamin, 1962-1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clemens, Cyril, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Coale, Joan, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Columbia University, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Columbus Museum of Art, 1934-1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Cone, Michelle N. C., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Connecticut Commission on the Arts, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - CORE, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cowles, Russell and Nancy, 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1972-1974; 1930 (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
  - Crawford, Sidney Peak, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - C, 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Daniels, Charles, 1926-1942 (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
  - DeVries, Peter and Katinka, 1974-1992 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Diamond, David, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Dickinson, E.W., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Diller, George E., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Downtown Gallery, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Driscoll, John Paul, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Edel, Leon, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Editions Richelieu, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Evergood, Phillip, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - "Exhibitions", 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Contains letters of praise from friends for exhibition openings
  - E, 1962-1982 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Fellows, James, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Fogg Art Museum, 1932-1976 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Ford Foundation, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Friend, David, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Gase, Dorothy, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Gilmore, Myron, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Goldfarb, Stephen, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Graziadei, Ercole, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Gross, Chaim and Renee, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1968-1980; 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - G, 1965-circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Hancock, Walker, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Hart Crane Newsletter, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Hersey, John, 1964-1982 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Hellman, Lillian, circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Hirsch, Joseph, 1951-1969 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Hirshhorn, Joseph and Olga, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Holsten, Nancy and Ned, 1951-circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Houston Museum of Fine Arts, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - H, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Imago Design Co., Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Ingersol, R. Sturgis, 1938-1955 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Isaacs, Stanley, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Johnson, Donna, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Josephson, Hannah and Matthew, circa 1950-1977 (Box 1, Folder 92-93)
  - Kantor, Sybil, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Karkadoulias Bronze Art, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Kaufmann, Edgar, 1938-1965 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Kirshner, Leon, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Kirstein, George, Jane and Paulina, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Knoedler and Co., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Kriss, Mark, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Lattimore, Richmond, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Life Magazine, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lighthill, Amy, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - LIndsey, Alexander, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1935-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - March, Florence and Frederic, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Markowitz, Gerald, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Martinu, Charlotte, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1942-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Midtown Galleries, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Modern Art Foundary, Inc., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Moe, Henry Allen, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Motive Magazine, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Muller, Steve, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Municipal Art Committee, New York City, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Academy of Design, 1935-1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Portrait Gallery, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newhaus, Eugene, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - New Britain Museum of American Art, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New York Times, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New-Times, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Neward Museum, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Newberry Library, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Nordness Gallery, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Norman, Charles, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Oldbourne Book Company LTD, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Osborn, Bob, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Owing, Nat (?), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pach, Walter, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Pei, I.M. (and Partners), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Piel, Mrs. Gerard, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Pinette, Carmen, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Porte (?), Katherine Anne, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Post Publishing Co., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Powell, Dawn, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pratt, George, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - P, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Randolph Macon Women's College, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Resor, Helen and Stanley, 1934-1974 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Reynolds, Louise, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Robert Schoelkopf Gallery, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Roberts, L.P., 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Robson, Peggy and Ernie, 1935-1930 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Rockefeller, Mrs. John D. (Abby), 1932-1940 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Roe, Anne, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Rutgers, 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - R, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Sachs, Paul J., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Saint Paul Art Center, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Saint-Gaudens Memorial, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Salisbury, Harrison, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Schwabacher, W.S., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Seven Gables Bookshop, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Sharrer, Honore, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Sheeler, Charles, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Shubert, Katherine, 1960-1977 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Shulman, Marshall, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Sims, Patterson, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Soby, James T., 1940-1963 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "South of Scranton", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Includes letters of congratulations for winning Carnegie Prize
  - Sotheby Parke Bernet, Inc., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Southern Illinois University, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Soyer, Moses, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Soyer, Raphael, 1967-1980 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Spock, Jane, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Stearn, Jimmy and Tonia, 1960-1995 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Stephan, David, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Stuyvesant, Felicia, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Styron, William, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Sweeny, James J., 1946-1967 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - S, circa 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Tallix, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Tate, Allen, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Taubes Copal, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Thurber, Helen, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Time Magazine, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Trapp, Frank A., 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Tuchmen, Barbara, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Tworkov, Jack, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - T, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - University of Nebraska, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - University of Vermont, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - University Prints, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - United States Army, 1942-1957 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Vassar College, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - The Visionary Company, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Visual Artists and Galleries Associations, Inc., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Vogue, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Volo, Sharon, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - V, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Wachs, Ethel and Paul, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Walsh, Alexander DeWitt, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Walter, Eda Loux, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Warren, Robert, Eleanor, Rosanna, and Gabriel, 1959-1983 (Box 2, Folder 102-103)
  - Washington Art Association, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Westcott, Glennary, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Weston, Christine, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - White, E.B., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Whitney, Betsey, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Whitney, Tom, Julia and Marguerite, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1951-1992 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Wilbur, Charlee and Richard, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - W, 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Yale University, 1952-1974 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Fragments and First Names Only, 1947-1976 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Letters from Peter Blume (Box 2)
    - Blankenhorn, Heber, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Blume, Grace, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Blume, Grace, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Blume, Grace, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Blume, Grace, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Blume, Rose, 1944-1966 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Letters from Grace Blume (Box 2)
    - Blume, Peter, circa 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Blume, Peter, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Blume, Peter, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Blankenhorn, Ann and Heber, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Craton, Marshall, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Holsten, Edward and Mrs., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Holsten, Edward and Mrs., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Letters from Grace Blume (Box 3)
    - Holsten, Edward and Mrs., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Condolence Letters, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Larkin to Ann Blankenhorn, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Writings and Notes, 1929-1986; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3, 9
  Writings by Blume include a travel journal, a notebook, lists of works of art, lectures, talks, and other writings about his art, about other artists and friends, and about art in general. Writings by others include theses and scholarly papers on Blume and poetry. Also found is a selection of criticism on The Rock, written by school children.
  - Travel Journal, by Peter Blume, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    from South Pacific cruise
  - Notebook, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    on Arshille Gorky's suicide
  - On Picasso's Guernica, by Peter Blume, Talk at Valentine Gallery, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes printed materials
  - "The Artists Responsibility as a Citizen," by Peter Blume, Lecture from The Arts, Sciences and Professions in the Post-War World Conference, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Modern Artists on Artists of the Past," by Peter Blume, Lecture for Conference at Musuem of Modern Art, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Statement on the Trial of 11 Communists, by Peter Blume, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "A Tribute to Charles Burchfield," by Peter Blume, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - On Louis Bouche, by Peter Blume, Talk from American Academy in Rome Annual Meeting of Board of Trustees, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Julian Levy," by Peter Blume, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - On His Art, by Peter Blume, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - On Rueben Nakian, by Peter Blume, Speech for Medal Ceremony of American Academy of Arts and Letters, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - On Recollection of the Flood, by Peter Blume, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - On Alexander Calder, by Peter Blume, Speech from Presenting A.C. Gold Medal for Sculpture, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Ivan Lorraine Albright," by Peter Blume, circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - On Hart Crane, by Peter Blume, 1929; circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Also includes "The Bridge," by Hart Crane
  - Notes for Unidentified Lectures and Talks, circa 1960-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)